<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Fuck Up Some Comics</title>
        <link>http://fuckupsomecomics.com/</link>
        <description>One more blog about story pictures</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 16 Jun 2017 02:22:26 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs>
        <generator>Feed for Node.js</generator>
        <image>
            <title>Fuck Up Some Comics</title>
            <url>https://ih0.redbubble.net/image.218095360.8037/st%2Csmall%2C215x235-pad%2C210x230%2Cf8f8f8.lite-1u2.jpg</url>
            <link>http://fuckupsomecomics.com/</link>
        </image>
        <copyright>All rights reserved 2017, Austin Lanari</copyright>
        <category>comics</category>
        <category>manga</category>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I Used T-- I still write about comics]]></title>
            <link>http://fuckupsomecomics.com/posts/1</link>
            <guid>http://fuckupsomecomics.com/posts/1</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 31 May 2017 21:12:03 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Is this thing on?]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Deja vu</em> eh?</p>
<p>When I started <em>Retcon Rasengan</em> I did it because I needed a place where I wouldn’t feel pressure to get things out on deadlines.  I also wanted to be able to do whatever I wanted format-wise and not feel bad about egregious picture placement or egregious word-vomit of the type I’m already indulging in now.</p>
<div style="">
  <figure class="floatCenter">
    <a target='_blank' href="http://retconrasengan.blogspot.com/2016/04/hand-sewn-domestic-female-aesthetic.html">
      <img class="linkImage" style="max-height: 380px;padding: 30px; background-color: rgba(92,107,192, 0.1);border-radius: 3px;" src="https://2.bp.blogspot.com/-0ipM8FHFpYo/VxaLuN9yRqI/AAAAAAAAFuM/mncK6PMa-Ccscl8Z1mgBgBltXv5Eu6TWQCKgB/w1200-h630-p-k-no-nu/kendrafemaleaestetic.png">
    </a>
    <figcaption style="color: black;margin-top: -30px;">RR was shortlived; my interview with Kendra Josie Kirkpatrick was a highlight</figcaption>
  </figure>
</div>
<p>But I was going through some shit.</p>
<p>By the time early 2016 rolled around, I had been out of my Master’s program for a full year and had no prospects for a job.  I started working part-time for a non-profit, which was certainly better than 1. nothing and 2. washing dishes; but… well, you get it, I hope.</p>
<p>And I was so hungry to write. I started with the lovely folks at <a target='_blank' href='http://comicbastards.com'>Comic Bastards</a> when Dustin gave me a chance to shit up his sight fawning over <em>Naruto</em> or spewing typographic venom at the very concept of motion comics.  I reached out to <a target='_blank' href='http://loser-city.com'>Loser City</a> to write even more, and have the unique pleasure of both resurrecting and re-murdering their newsletter.  I wrote a couple of pieces for Comics Beat after being approached by somebody who just straight up stopped responding to my DMs, which I mention not to be passive-aggressive but only because it’s all pure humor to me now.  And, of course, the incomparable Danny Elk-elks started pestering me around the time RR was burning up in the atmosphere, pelting me with the absolute weirdest shit I had ever seen.  I still write for him over at <a target='_blank' href='http://comicsbulletin.com'>Comics Bulletin</a> and will continue to do so.</p>
<div style="">
  <figure class="floatCenter">
    <a target='_blank' href="http://comicsbulletin.com/tiny-pages-made-ashes-51917-mirror-mirror-ii/">
    <img style="padding: 30px; background-color: rgba(92,107,192, 0.1); max-height: 480px;border-radius: 3px;" src="https://i2.wp.com/comicsbulletin.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/Mirror-Mirror-II-cover.jpg?fit=798%2C1200" alt="Mirror Mirror II Review">
    </a>
    <figcaption style="color:black;margin-top:-30px;">Peep my in-depth review of Mirror Mirror II</figcaption>
  </figure>
</div>
<p>I also once e-mailed Andrew Wheeler to write for Comics Alliance.  He never got back to me.</p>
<p>A better summation of my clout I cannot figure.</p>
<p>I really enjoyed doing it.  Nothing felt better to me than when I would crush a book in a day or two and then proceed to wade through the canals that had formed in the space between my feelings and the most prominent artistic outcroppings of any given work.  If I write anything, it’s because I felt like I could at least convey that to a <em>single</em> person other than myself in a way that felt efficacious and sincere and not forced or pithy.</p>
<p>But the problem lies there as well.  Maybe it’s not just comics twitter, but at certain points. the cynicism is infectious, and your ability to calibrate your motivations based on your own compass becomes seriously compromised when you let your empathy feed your self-pity rather than mediating the two. It’s just so easy to internalize all the negativity in comic-dom, both the inevitable stuff and the nasty nastiness.</p>
<p>Criticism, or even straight-up exploring a work in terms of what parts of it worked for you, is a way to share excitement and to share frustration; it is, somehow, simultaneously cathartic and taxing in ways that are hard to balance. If you leave that fucking sharingan on you can glean a lot, but you’re going to fuck up your day; you were just trying to read a funnybook, you utter clown.</p>
<p>I hope this is not trite, but it is a privilege to be able and willing to make the commitment to write regularly in general, let alone analyze, let alone share one’s thoughts about works that others have created, or already engaged with in ways that often seem more interesting.  Life balance plays a huge part in that privilege, and it was one that I lacked as RR tapered off and one that I am lucky to have now. None of this is to even mention the fact that I have the unfortunately ultimate privilege of being a cis-het straight white guy who does not have to worry about the way in which a given space might respond to my particular voice.</p>
<p>Nobody is wrong for walking away. Often it is very obviously not a <em>lack</em> of conviction that takes some of our most talented brothers and sisters out of the spotlight. Nobody has to do this. I mean, nobody has to do anything as far as hobbies go, right? And certainly nobody has to do <em>this</em>, this fucking… what? Hobby <em>about</em> a hobby?</p>
<p>But for me, I know I wasn’t giving it my all.  And in the last year, I learned that I actually have one of those: an “all”.  I also found my “give a shit” as well as my “some semblance of time management,” as if to feign adulthood.</p>
<p>More importantly, I love that navigation I mentioned earlier.  That tug-of-war between what seems to be the work-in-itself and my own reaction to it. When a book really clicks and you feel like you are on the same wavelength not as the author but the wavelength of the <em>book</em>, the <em>panel</em>, that <em>layout</em>– when you can speak truth to the beauty in the rickety joints of that good ol’ visual narrative syntax, it feels like walking somewhere you shouldn’t be.</p>
<p>The world seems bigger because you get to open up a space between yourself and a piece of art. There’s a beautiful vulnerability there, opening your viewpoint to be part of this shared experience.</p>
<p>It’s late, and I’ve spent enough time on me.</p>
<img style="max-height: 480px;" src="http://fuckupsomecomics.com/posts/1/future_hendrix.png" alt="And so" />
<p>Let’s fuck up some comics.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Red Sprite was my Shit]]></title>
            <link>http://fuckupsomecomics.com/posts/2</link>
            <guid>http://fuckupsomecomics.com/posts/2</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2017 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Red Sprite wasn't the best or brightest of its class, but it's still gone too soon.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<img class="floatCenter" style="max-height: 600px;" src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/foggy1/WSJ_Issue_39_2016_Cover.png" />
<p>Last summer, three titles joined the Shonen Jump lineup in quick succession:  Yamamoto Ryouhei’s fan-servicey <em>Love Rush!</em>, artist/writer duo Demizu Posuka &amp; Shirai Kaiu’s cerebral thriller <em>Promised Neverland</em>, and Yagi Tomohiro’s brilliant but boneheaded <em>Red Sprite</em>.</p>
<p>Can you tell how I feel about each one?</p>
<p>Of the three titles, <em>Promised Neverland</em> is the only one still running, and has been a smash hit, regularly placing in the top 5 titles that <em>Jump</em> serializes every week according to reader surveys. Demizu’s art, frankly, is several echelons below the Tabatas and Horikoshis of the world just pages away, who are cranking out savant-like sequences on a regular basis. Author Shirai, however, has gifted Demizu an absolutely <em>killer</em> main plot and drafts the most suspenseful chapters of any series in Jump, save for when Oda decides to really do his thing. Demizu isn’t particularly <em>bad</em> necessarily; the color page spreads are often pleasant and monstrous images grab the reader with Demizu’s subdued-yet-jaunty style. Where Demizu shines is in layering the elements of a given story beat to really drive home certain narrative choke-points in Shirai’s writing.</p>
<div class='floatCenter' style='text-align:center;'>
  <img style="display: inline-block;max-height: 600px;margin:10px;" src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/foggy1/Screenshot_2017-06-06-21-22-50-01.jpeg" />
  <img style="display: inline-block;max-height: 600px;margin:10px;" src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/foggy1/Screenshot_2017-06-06-21-16-55-01.jpeg" />
  <figcaption>Left (or top on mobile): Shirai & Demizu have a great rhythm, building up to this page as a big reveal while still finding room to rotate voices and keep things moving. Right (bottom on mobile): Yagi is all bluster, with half of the early chapters being this old guy yelling.</figcaption>
</div>
<p>Almost immediately, if presented with <em>Promised Neverland</em> and <em>Red Sprite</em>, you would be able to guess which would survive serialization, given the stark contrast between the two. Where <em>PN</em> delays the payoff until the next chapter and incrementally delivers an increase in tension, <em>RS</em> will stoke a conflict only to immediately resolve it in the next chapter with little indication of why the reader should return again.</p>
<hr/>
<figure class='floatCenter'>
<img class="floatCenter" style="max-height: 600px;" src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/foggy1/Screenshot_2017-06-06-21-55-07-01.jpeg" />
<figcaption>Red Sprite tells the tale of orphans with metal in their bones who are harvested for energy to fuel warships. Post time-skip, main character Tatsu Frampt forms a nation in the sky to gather his scattered friends under one banner.</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Still, there are a lot of layers to why <em>Red Sprite</em> works as a story. First of all, the allegory of a certain class living humans being used as energy sources for the rest of society is still terrifying enough to punch through its own thin veil. Second, it provides a nuanced platform to give these kids their powers: the very thing that makes them valuable and exploitable is one-and-the-same with what empowers them to fight their oppressors. A nice bonus, of course, is that Yagi gets to draw big dramatic lightning strikes in every single fight.</p>
<figure class='floatCenter'>
<img class="floatCenter" style="max-height: 600px;" src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/foggy1/Screenshot_2017-06-06-21-19-29-01.jpeg" />
<figcaption>Pages like this one demonstrate Yagi might not have even fully understood what he had. Puerile classism is nowhere near as scary as the alleged hyper-pragmatism that drives the decision making of the real villains.</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Where <em>Red Sprite</em> fell flat was the fact that it mainly emphasized the two points above and readers were unwilling in the time allotted to see beyond into the nuanced, layered world that Yagi was on the cusp of creating. He was setting out to tell a story not only about resistance, but of some of the scariest things that drive oppression. The villains were not *scary dudes* or *zomg so strong* without context. Rather, they were holdovers from a time where war was necessary for them to survive. <em>Red Sprite</em> was setting up to tell a tale where the villains were not just a bunch of fascists hardened by years of war with devastating weapons at their fingertips due to years of military innovation. In <em>Red Sprite</em> the weapons and the humans that wield them are the same.</p>
<p>Both sides, good and evil, have their humanity circumscribed by horrifying technological innovations that bring in to question the very essence of their souls. For Tatsu Frampt and crew, the question of humanity is an afterthought: this is a country whose sovereign goal is merely to regather a group of childhood friends under a single banner. By contrast, the hyper-militaristic meat-heads who aim to quash the young rebellion possess the very same powers, and only know how to abuse them. Their humanity is forfeit not because of the plasmarrow in their bones but rather because war has warped their sense of purpose, and wielding power for its own sake is all that makes sense anymore.</p>
<p>Even this take, however, is too simplistic, and Yagi was well aware of that. The apotheosis of his vision for the series lies in the Ash Soldier, the final villain that the crew faces before this story comes to its abrupt end. The Ash Soldier is horrifying in appearance, and perhaps even scarier in concept.</p>
<div class='floatCenter' style='text-align:center;'>
  <img style="display: inline-block;max-height: 600px;margin: 5px;" src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/foggy1/Screenshot_2017-05-18-09-17-36-01.jpeg" />
  <img style="display: inline-block;max-height: 600px;margin: 5px;" src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/foggy1/Screenshot_2017-05-18-09-17-42-01.jpeg" />
</div>
<p>The Ash Soldier is explained to have been a weapon invented during a time when the fascist empire of Edenia was just trying to fight a war. The soldier himself appears to be nothing but his consciousness and his bones, which serve as a substratum for the ashes of fallen soldiers whose collective speed and strength he appears to inherit.</p>
<p>But of course, the war is over, and all that is left is subjugation. So Blackburn, a storied Ash Soldier, sits and waits. I mean, holy shit. Just look at that. He <em>sits</em> and <em>waits</em> for a jolt of lightning to carry him down to a battle field where dozens of his compatriots have perished, <em>because</em> dozens of his compatriots have perished. His summoning simultaneously represents his army’s failure and its triumph, since his presence means that the soldiers are more powerful in death.</p>
<p>Damn.</p>
<p>And I still have so many questions. Does Blackburn actually <em>have</em> a consciousness of his own? Does it really inhabit his bones or is it like, a collective consciousness like some kind of cross between a Borg and a Cylon? Does he feel pain? Does he really just… sit there, all the time… waiting?</p>
<p>Ultimately I understand why this series got canned: for all the intrigue and nuance loaded into this world in ways that don’t immediately present themselves, what the reader <em>actually</em> gets each chapter is a whole lot of bluster and very little payoff. Frampt continuously shows up to steal the show and does just that. Rescue missions go off without a hitch, and entire countries are saved almost instantly on his arrival. While certainly any number of these editorial decisions were made because this series never got out of the basement tier of reader surveys, for so much conflict to be stacked up and resolved in the span of two volumes is a little overboard.</p>
<figure class='floatCenter'>
<img style="max-height: 700px;" src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/foggy1/Screenshot_2017-06-06-21-09-44-01.jpeg " />
</figure>
<p>“<em>One day you will turn to ash as well.</em>” The above page depicting Blackburn’s death is the stylistic highpoint of the series; unfortunately, it comes too late. The warship juxtaposed with the sun amidst a halo of clouds plays off of Blackburn’s collapsing ash figure as everything dissolves around a lone eyeball. The only reason the image doesn’t play <em>even better</em> is because Yagi frequently made use of similar shots in which the solitary warship stood dwarfed by the sky in a large, top-half panel.</p>
<p>It sounds weird, but Yagi spent <em>too</em> much time on making things happen. Early chapters of <em>Black Clover</em> fell similarly flat for me because the only thing carrying them was Tabata’s incredible line-work. Still, this was Yagi’s second shot at serialization after his initial Gold Future Cup performance earned him a spot in the lineup with <em>Iron Knight</em>, and I can’t help but hope he gets another shot. There was a lot underneath the surface of <em>Red Sprite</em> and not enough of it was excavated. I would love to see Yagi try again with a more mature take on a series, as he has demonstrated the capability of some pretty memorable (and conceptually disturbing!) imagery that could carry a longer series; as long as less superficial chest-puffing gets in the way.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A Hollowing]]></title>
            <link>http://fuckupsomecomics.com/posts/3</link>
            <guid>http://fuckupsomecomics.com/posts/3</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jun 2017 09:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Even without color, Sloane finds surprising ways to innovate.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>When finally breaking open my Short Box, I went straight for Sloane’s <em>A Hollowing</em>.</p>
<p>…</p>
<p>Ok, so I actually ate the candy. But THEN, I read <em>A Hollowing</em>.</p>
<img class="floatCenter" style="max-height: 600px;" src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/foggy1/a_hollowing.png" />
<p>I’ve been writing about Sloane’s work ever since I started taking writing about comics seriously and I don’t think that’s a coincidence. Sloane makes it easy to take comics seriously. Her work on <em>From Under Mountains</em> <a target='_blank' href="http://retconrasengan.blogspot.com/2016/01/hanharas-grasp-letting-world-tell-story.html">remains some of my favorite work</a> in the past few years, and her Patreon is a consistent source of the same quality of work.</p>
<p>There is a constant sense that Sloane is in charge of the layout, rather than the other way around. Her work in <em>FUM</em> is evidence of this, as are the snippets of projects on her Patreon. For Sloane, layouts are a means of juxtaposing not only story beats, but also colors and textures; and often that juxtaposing extends to the third dimension wherein the story takes on layers that often carry you between physical spaces.</p>
<p>(Seriously, some of the best examples of this are on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/sloane">her Patreon</a>, and I’m not going to post work from there even though I’m DYING to talk about some of those pages, so check them out or be on the lookout for new work.)</p>
<p><em>A Hollowing</em> leans more on the metaphorical space of dream-like (mostly nightmarish) imagery to guide the reader. It is a tale of trauma, the ways in which trauma resurfaces, and the ways in which we must confront the things that hurt us to move forward and survive in some kind of imperfect union. The tale unfolds through the eyes of a young girl, the loss of her mother, and a new horse.</p>
<p>Told entirely in black and white, with many more “conventional” layouts than one might find in her other work, Sloane instead leans heavily on ink itself as a presence on the page, with the horse being the best example. This adds to the dreamlike effect of the gray, inkless watercolors that demarcate memories, which <em>itself</em> adds to scenes where the grays and inks meet in a collision of present and past traumas for the main character.</p>
<figure class='floatCenter'>
<img class="floatCenter" style="max-height: 600px;" src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/foggy1/door_wipe.png" />
</figure>
<p>Above, the main character catches her father doing something you would rather not catch your father doing, and then flees to her room where she falls asleep and wakes up in a dream. The somewhat abrupt shift from running away to being in bed (particularly as juxtaposed between seeing her father through two doorways in a way that appears unsettling) captures the anxiety of being a kid seeing something you shouldn’t: it’s a whirlwind until you’re somewhere safe, and even then you’re usually caught stuck with your heart beating fast, going over what happened. Sloane captures that latter moment in the penultimate panel before launching us into a nasty flashback. A solid page, but still more layers to parse.</p>
<p>In what appears to be a pretty standard layout, with “only” black and white at her disposal and no layered panels, Sloane still pulls off her trick of using overlayed elements to bridge the space between panels, not just once, but <em>twice</em>.</p>
<p>The sheepish “Beeps” that surround the final panel in which the main character finds herself in a car begin in the panel in which she drifts off to sleep, rendering a quick panel transition as being one that occurs much more gradually.</p>
<p>And then there’s the ink swipe. A smudge almost like a tire track, running from her father’s bedroom door in the upper right of the page, to her waking-into-a-dream consciousness in the bottom left. The pronounced gutters of this story–this page being no exception–preclude any serious layering from occurring, so the light touch here is just enough to traverse the normal series of events without taking the reader completely out of the page. To wit, I didn’t really absorb this smudge until the second time I read the story.</p>
<p>The implications are clear: though her nightmares unearth past trauma <em>for the reader</em>, it’s the <em>current trauma</em> of what she sees through her father’s door that does the unearthing <em>for her</em>. The ink swipe physically connects points A and B on the page through the physical doorways she uses to traverse the house; it also connects the two beats where she simply lays her head down to sleep, the means by which she travels from the waking world to somewhere much darker.</p>
<p>Without the “Beeps” and without the ink swipe, this page serves its purpose. Yet, these things aren’t window dressing: they are real, substantial parts of the story that augment the narrative in ways that additional panels could not achieve. They add ambiance, they alter our perception of the page’s pace, and they help round out the menacing tone of what is occurring and how it connects to what is to come. It is worth noting that the real punctuation to the events of this sequence does come two pages later, on the page turn, so the heightened sense of anticipation plays.</p>
<p>There’s far more to talk about as far as <em>A Hollowing</em> is concerned, as the story on its own merits critical attention. I, however, am stuck as usual, marveling at the fact that regardless of the tools, Sloane demonstrates the full narrative depth of the medium.</p>
<p><a target=_blank href="https://twitter.com/AustinLanari/status/873991542649876480"><em>I made a thread for my thoughts on the other Short Box titles</em></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>